Guide to the Maurice Isserman Oral History Interviews OH.036
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Maurice Isserman Oral History Interviews
1977-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Isserman, Maurice
OH.036
1.5 Linear Feet in cassette boxes & manuscript box
103 sound discs (cd) in 2 cassette boxes
64 Cassettes in 2 cassette boxes
1 manuscript boxes with transcripts
This group of interviews was donated to the Tamiment Library by historian Maurice Isserman following the publication of "If I Had a Hammer.. .The Death of the Old Left and the Birth of the New Left" (Basic Books, Inc.: New York, 1987). Isserman conducted the interviews between 1983 and 1986. Some time between 2002 and 2012, he also donated a transcript for an interview he conducted with Jeff Jones and Eleanor Stein for a separate project he intended to pursue--a the history of the Weathermen--but never followed up on.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Maurice Isserman and later found in repository, dates unknown. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2000.023 and 2015.033.
Scope and Contents
This group of interviews was donated to the Tamiment Library by historian Maurice Isserman following the publication of "If I Had a Hammer.. .The Death of the Old Left and the Birth of the New Left" (Basic Books, Inc.: New York, 1987). Isserman conducted the interviews between 1983 and 1986. Some time between 2002 and 2012, he also donated a transcript for an interview he conducted with Jeff Jones and Eleanor Stein for a separate project he intended to pursue--a the history of the Weathermen--but never followed up on. SCOPE AND CONTENT NOTE: Isserman sought the roots of 1960s radicalism in the American Communist Party, the various groups led by Max Shachtman, the journal Dissent, and the Committee for Non-Violent Action. He conducted interviews with intellectuals and political partisans active in the 1950s and the 1960s, among them, Stanley Aronowitz, David Dellinger, Ralph DiGia, Hal Draper, Harry and Vera Fleischman, Manny Geltman, Todd Gitlin, Abraham (Al) Glotzer, Gordon Haskell, Richard Healy, Michael Walzer, Irving Howe, Julius and Phyllis Jacobson, David McReynolds, Debbie Meier, Juanita and Wally Nelson, Ronald Radosh, and Andre Schiffrin. Index available in repository. Contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu for information.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
New Left -- United States.; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.
- If I Had a Hammer
  - Stanley Aronowitz, Jul 11, 1984; cuid116 (Box 4, Cassette 1, Box 2, Cd 1)
  - Albert Bigelow, Dec 15, 1984; cuid33675 (Box 2, Cd 2A-B, Box 4, Cassette 2A-B)
  - Lewis Coser, May 3, 1985; cuid117 (Box 4, Cassette 3, Box 2, Cd 3)
  - David Dellinger, Jan 24, 1985; cuid118 (Box 4, Cassette 4A-B, Box 2, Cd 4A-B)
  - Betty Denitch, Aug 6, 1984; cuid119 (Box 4, Cassette 5A-C, Box 2, Cd 5A-C)
  - Bogdan Denitch, Dec 7, 1986; cuid120 (Box 4, Cassette 6, Box 2, Cd 6)
  - Ralph DiGia, Dec 7, 1986; cuid121 (Box 4, Cassette 7A-B, Box 2, Cd 7A-B)
  - Hal Draper, Dec 29, 1983; cuid33676 (Box 4, Cassette 8A-B, Box 2, Cd 1-3)
  - Barbara Eastman, Apr 21; cuid122 (Box 4, Cassette 9, Box 2, Cd 9)
  - Harry and Vera Fleischman, undated; cuid123 (Box 4, Cassette 10, Box 2, Cd 10)
  - Manny Geltman, Mar 19, 1985; cuid124 (Box 4, Cassette 11A-B, Box 2, Cd 11A-B)
  - Todd Gitlin, Dec 29, 1984; cuid125 (Box 4, Cassette 12A-B, Box 2, Cd 12A-B)
  - Al Glotzer, Oct 4, 1984; cuid126 (Box 4, Cassette 13A-B, Box 2, Cd 13A-B)
  - Gordon Haskell, Jul 15, 1983; cuid127 (Box 4, Cassette 14A-B, Box 2, Cd 14A-B)
  - Richard Healy, 1982; cuid128 (Box 4, Cassette 15A-C, Box 2, Cd 15A-C)
  - Michael Walzer, Mar 20, 1986; cuid129 (Box 4, Cassette 16A-B, Box 2, Cd 16A-B)
  - Irving Howe, Jan 24, 1982; Oct 21, 1982; cuid130 (Box 4, Cassette 17A-D, Box 2, Cd 17A-D)
    Scope and Contents
    On side 2 of the January 24, 1982 Irving Howe interview (CD 17B, "Side 2"), the interview ends at the 2 1/2 minute mark. There is a previous political interview with an unidentified source that may be of interest.
  - Julius and Phyllis Jacobson, Apr 21, 1984; cuid131 (Box 4, Cassette 18, Box 2, Cd 18)
  - Arthur Lipow, Sep 11, 1984; cuid132 (Box 5, Cassette 19A-B, Box 2, Cd 19A-B)
  - David McReynolds, Jul 9, 1984; cuid133 (Box 5, Cassette 20A-B, Box 3, Cd 20A-B)
  - Steve Max, May 14, 1986; cuid134 (Box 5, Cassette 22A-B, Box 3, Cd 22A-B)
  - Debbie Meier, Apr 19, 1986; cuid135 (Box 5, Cassette 23, Box 3, Cd 23)
  - Juanita and Wally Nelson, Jul 10, 1985; cuid136 (Box 5, Cassette 24, Box 3, Cd 24A-B)
  - Joni Rabinowitz, Jul 15, 1983; cuid137 (Box 5, Cassette 25, Box 3, Cd 25)
  - Ronald Radosh, Jul 10, 1984; cuid138 (Box 5, Cassette 26, Box 3, Cd 26)
  - Bernard Rosenberg, Oct 16, 1983; cuid139 (Box 5, Cassette 27A-B, Box 3, Cd 27A-B)
  - Andre Schiffrin, Jun 19, 1983; cuid140 (Box 5, Cassette 28, Box 3, Cd 28)
  - Mike Thelwel, Jul 10, 1986; cuid141 (Box 5, Cassette 29, Box 3, Cd 29)
  - Freijof Thygessen, Dec 8, 1984; cuid142 (Box 5, Cassette 30, Box 3, Cd 30)
    Recording was made in a public setting and includes background noise that sometimes makes the conversation difficult to hear.
  - Dorothy Tristman and Larry Wittner, Jul 4, 1984; cuid143 (Box 5, Cassette 31A-B, Box 3, Cd 31A-B)
  - Peggy Dennis, undated; cuid144 (Box 5, Cassette 32, Box 3, Cd 32)
  - Ben Dvosin, undated; cuid145 (Box 5, Cassette 33A-C, Box 3, Cd 33A-C)
    All recordings had a slight static electrical interference noise.
  - Max Gordon, Feb 15, 1977; cuid146 (Box 5, Cassette 34, Box 3, Cd 34)
    Static electrical interference noise present in original recording
  - Gil Green, Dec 31, 1977; cuid33677 (Box 3, Cd Green 1-2, Box 5, Cassette 35A-B)
  - Vincent Lossowski, Jun 19, 1978; cuid147 (Box 5, Cassette 36, Box 3, Cd 36)
  - Steve Nelson, undated; cuid148 (Box 5, Cassette 37A-B, Box 3, Cd 37A-B)
  - Morris Schappes, Dec 29, 1977; cuid149 (Box 5, Cassette 38, Box 3, Cd 38)
  - George Watt, undated; cuid150 (Box 5, Cassette 39A-C, Box 3, Cd 39A-C)
    Cross-talk and some static electrical interference noise in original recording
- History of the Weathermen
  - Jeff Jones and Eleanor Stein Interview Transcript, September 16, 1989; cuid33678 (Box 1)
- Interview Transcripts
  - Interview Transcripts - Preservation Masters, cuid33680 (Box 1)
  - Interview Transcripts - User Copies, 1977-1986; cuid33679 (Box 6)
    Scope and Content Note
    Includes transcripts for some of the interviews conducted for "If I Had A Hammer," and one for (a never embarked-upon) project on the history of the Weathermen.